Hi, welcome back to the lamrim. We're on episode 11. It's called Making it on the Tennis Team.
And we're going to start out with a story from the lamrim about MCHOG ZUNG  and MCHOG means supreme
and ZUNG means
A pair of two people.
And this is an important word in in secret practice and I can't tell you about it.
But anyway MCHOG ZUNG means the big two.
And this refers to two of the most famous disciples of Lord Buddha,
which are Shariputra and Maudgalyayana.
We know Shariputra because he's the hero in the Heart Sutra.
He gets to ask a question and because of his question
we find we get the Heart Sutra. We get to hear the whole Heart Sutra.
The Buddha, it by the way, it is
traditionally
taught
that these two disciples of the Buddha became
arhats.  They reached nirvana.
But they reached it on a lower track. So they're in this category, both of them are in this category
of people who have reached a very high
personal space
where they are in complete bliss and they kind of
are are not so interested
in the bodhisattva ideal of trying to
meet every living being,
and
give this promise to them that, "I will take care of you."
They traditionally, they're having too much bliss
in nirvana to to think about that much. So it happened one day
that
Lord Buddha
came to these two
and I don't know if he shook them awake or I don't know how he did it, but he,
he said, "You know, I want to teach you guys about this higher thing
where you take care of everybody and I want you to have this personal experience where you meet
every living being. I think it will change your life forever." So he encouraged them
and the reply by these two
arhats was,
NGO MTSAR, NGO MTSAR BA 'DUG KYANG
NGO MTSAR  BA 'DUG KYANG
In the second line here Seiji, probably.
NGO MTSAR BA 'DUG KYANG
"Wow that sounds amazing, you know, to meet every
single living being that, yeah, that would be something special."
KYANG, but,
BDAG CAG NI SDONG DUM MES TSIG PA
BZHIN DU GYUR PAS
"Ever since we reached nirvana
we've been like a bump on a log."
It says here a tree trunk burned by
a,
an inert tree trunk
burned by fire or something like that.
But what it means is, "You know, we're just totally out of it
that sounds wonderful Buddha, but
you know,
don't teach this stuff to us. We're already in this kind of
spaced out place
and we're going to be here for millions of years,
you know." So CI BYAR
CI BYAR MI 'DUG
"We're not the people to be teaching this stuff to because we're already,
we're already wrapped up in our personal nirvana.
You're kind of wasting your time with us."
So there's this incident
where even this great
arhat who who requested the Heart Sutra,
was staying in this kind of space and told Lord Buddha,
"Maybe you shouldn't waste your time on us
because,
because we're in a bad,  we're in a good bad place
and we we can't really do it."
MI 'DUG CES GSOL BAR GSUNGS PA
'PHAGS PA SH'A RI'I BU LTA BU SPRUL PA'I NYAN THOS
Then Pabongka Rinpoche
comes to
Shariputra's defense
And he says, "Look, Shariputra, this arya,
he was just faking it.
He had not entered a selfish
personal nirvana. He was just faking it."
And the answer he gave,
'You know, don't waste your time on us,'
was for the benefit of other people."
Which is ...
NYAN THOS RANG MTSAN PA GZHAN LA DGONGS NAS GSUNGS
This DGONGS means
You know, he was faking it.
Shariputra was faking it and he was trying to be a good example
for the other potential
nirvana seekers in their group, in their student group, He was trying to say don't make the same mistake I made.
Don't become
immune
to the higher teachings. Don't make this mistake. I made that mistake. You guys don't make it.
But he was just faking it.
So he's one of those people like in the Heart Sutra,
that by tradition might even be considered a Buddha
asking another buddha question. Who's the other Buddha in this case? For zero dollars?
Avolokiteshvara, bodhisattva.
RANG MTSAN PA GZHAN LA DGONGS NAS GSUNGS PA BZHIN 'TSANG RGYAB  LA BAR CHAD CHE,
Anyway,
reaching this lower nirvana
is a big obstacle to tsangyalwa which is the verb for?
Buddhahood, to become a Buddha. Okay.
DES NA
Therefore
RANG RES NGES 'BYUNG GI BLO LA MYONG BA THON PA NA
So should we skip all the
stages of the lamrim
which are meant for people of lower capacity or medium
capacity? "Are you telling me
that we should just skip those lower steps?"
And the answer is, no.
MYONG BA THON PA
means get good at
being sad about the state of the world.
Get good at being sad about the state of the world.
Get good at it and then,
THEG CHEN GYI LAM LA NGES PAR 'JUG DGOS,
You must
enter the greater way.
You must seek this experience where you meet
all the living beings in the universe,
and personally commit to them to help them. Okay?
'JUG
SKYES BU 'BRING DANG THUN MONG BA'I LAM LA BLO SBYANGS PA NI,
NGES 'BYUNG RGYUD LA SKYE BA'I CHED YIN GYI,
The purpose for studying the steps of the path
for people of medium capacity
is to get this kind of state of mind where we are tired of
all,
all the kinds of life you could live in this, in this samsara. Okay in the suffering life, okay?
Even a human life. Even a wealthy human life. Even a wealthy human life with lots of
scriptures around. Mixed Nuts.
Okay, even those we don't want, we want to go beyond those.
LAM DNGOS LA 'GRO BA'I PHYIR MIN NO,,
but
It's not the real path. Wow.
It's necessary to get to the real path,
but it's not the real path. It is a part of the
steps of the path
But it's not the path you want to get on in the end.
all right, uh,
LAM GYI DNGOS GZHI NI, SKYES BU CHEN PO'I BYANG CHUB SEMS SBYONG STE,
Then he says something kind of radical and  I've seen people misunderstand the statement.
How do you say it?
He says, can you show the next picture?
I like this next picture.
I don't know about you, but, you know,
and I haven't gone to a lot of concerts in my life. But, in this next picture
you see uh...
Okay, well, who are these guys?
they're playing pretty bad. I'll tell you that,
and they're the opening act. Okay. They're the opening act. And I don't know, like
you buy a ticket for a great band,
you want to go see them in live, in person.
You know. It's a two-hour, three-hour concert.
And when you get there
there's some other dumb band playing,
who are not very good and they're called the opening act. In English, they're called the opening act. These are...
I don't know, somehow they got this job
to play for an hour to waste time
so the real superstar guys, could you know relax in the back.
And you have to sit through these guys for an hour. Okay, what's that got to do with anything?
Uh
And then sometimes by the way,
the superstar comes on plays two songs goes away and the bad band comes back. That's what's happening with the lamrim.
The first part we started...
The first part we studied
the steps of the path for people of
lesser capacity or medium capacity.
People who just want to stay out of the lower realms or
people who just want to stay out of any rebirth in general.
Tho, all of those people
they're not the real practice. They're just the warm-up band.
They're just the opening act band. They're not the, what do you call that, you call opening act?
There's another name.
Yeah, anyway.
This
steps of the path that we spent years on, that's not the real thing.  That's not
the real concert.
That's not the music of the lamrim.
That was just to warm you up.
And by the way, and then he says something radical.
Okay, you ready for this?
The six perfections
are also the opening act coming back at the end.
are, are also opening act, they're not the main thing and that's a,
it's an incredible statement.
The steps of the path
to get out of a lower birth or to get out of birth in general, they're not the main thing. And
the six perfections are not the main thing. So, what's that leave?
Yeah, it's the experience of of meeting everybody in the universe and committing to each one,
individually. "I will help you." You know that
Pabongka Rinpoche is making a very radical statement. That's the main act. That's the Rolling Stones.
That's the thing you've been waiting to hear.
And that's what I want you to focus on.,
Very extraordinary statement. I mean if you're a real buddhist practitioner, you're like wow, that's pretty heavy.
All right
DES NA SKYES BU CHEN PO'I LAM LA SLOB PA LA DANG PO SPRO BA BSKYED PA'I PHYIR DU,
So,
great lamas have
written advertisements
for
this studying,
studying this greater way, studying the path of a bodhisattva. Great lamas in the past
have done a sales job
for this bodhichitta,
for trying to get this bodhichitta,
for trying to have this experience.
And one of them is the great fifth Dalai Lama.
Who lived
1617 to 1682
?
And he wrote a book called 'JAM DPAL ZHAL LUNG
Which we have studied already.
It's called the Word of Manjushri.
GSUNGS PA BZHIN
He lists
cool things
that are going to happen
if you get this experience. If you can just
get to this experience.
By the way which you have to do in meditation.
If you can just get to this experience
of meeting all these beings, just get to that.
SNGON DU BLANGS NAS 'CHAD PA PHYAG LEN DU. GSUNGS PA BZHIN
Ten different things are going to happen to you.
Now, they're not listed so clearly in that short lamrim. But in this long lamrim, they're covered in detail.
BLANGS NAS 'CHAD PA PHYAG LEN DU 291A *,,
YOD PAS DE LTAR BSHAD NA 'DI LA BCU,
So ever since the days of the Fifth Dalai Lama it's been
a tradition at this point
to introduce the students to 10 cool things that are
going to happen to you
if you can reach this peak experience
with every living being .
Let's go through the list
briefly
and then Pabongka Rinpoche is going to go into great detail. In fact,
the great detail that the lama goes into on these 10,
mean that we're not going to finish the 10 during this
retreat. We'll have to finish them in the next retreat.
But we'll get part way through the list. So 10
different amazing things.
Number one: if you have this experience with
every living being
10 special things are going to happen to you.
Number one:
THEG CHEN GYI 'JUG SGO SEMS BSKYED KHO NA RA BSTAN PA,
It's the only way
to enter the path of the, of the bodhisattvas,
is to have this experience.
There is no other way. You have to have this experience
There are many systems like rgyu dan menar dun
You know, The Seven Step Method or BDAG GZHAN MNYAM BRJE,
exchanging self and others.
But they are methods to get to this experience.
When you get to this experience,
only then can we say you're on the mahayana.
Then you're on, then you're on the higher
path and you don't have to go back
to pick up your lunch or something that you left at your house.
uh.
Second: RGYAL BA'I SRAS ZHES BYA BA'I MING THOB PA,
And I love this.
From the moment you have that experience,
and Buddhas talk about you, they will say
Tim, my son,
or Seiji, my son.
They will start to refer to you as their son
or your daughter? Okay, and that's such a sweet thing
when the Buddhas start talking to you, about you
as if you were really their son or daughter. And of course they love all living beings. Of course they
love all living beings equally.
But those living beings who are very close to joining
the family of enlightened beings, they have a special
feeling about them and they say my son,
they refer to them as my son or my daughter. And,
And it's very sweet, you know, if you've ever had this relationship.
I had this relationship with my,
my heart teacher, Khen Rinpoche. And when he, when people met him he would refer to me as his son.
And it was a very deep, deep love, deep thing. So.
When you, when you have this experience,
then the enlightened beings of the universe start saying oh, oh, he's, he's one of my sons or she's one of my daughters. Okay
Okay, benefit number three:
NYAN RANG RIGS KYI SGO NAS ZIL GYIS NON PA,
Then you join a family, you join a select family and you are completely different from other people, especially
people who are on lower path. You are totally, I like to think of it as
you are at an
evolutionary higher level. You are no longer
even in their
league.
You're in a different league. You're in a different family. Number four:
MCHOD PA'I ZHING MCHOG TU 'GYUR BA,
Something cool happens. I don't know this is kind of
sexy
but uh if you have had this experience
and
people
uh
respect you at all for that,
they get incredible good karma. So that's kind of a nice reason to have the experience. You see.
Then
after that if you're a nice person and people think you're nice,
then they get like 10 billion more seeds
uh
by thinking of you well. It's kind of, of a strange
benefit. Or they give you a cup of tea, then for them it's like
giving
a thousand cups of tea or a million cups of tea because you're a different person. You're, you're a different
being.
So it's kind of fun
to be a person who
if other people,
get to know you, then automatically they are making great karma.
All right, number five:
TSOGS RGYA CHEN PO BDE BLAG TU RDZOGS PA,
It's easy for you to collect massive amounts of good seeds. When you have that experience
you'll get a a number of seeds in your mind which is unimaginable and they will carry you to amazing places.
And you know that you, you see that.
SDIG SGRIB MYUR DU SBYANG BA,
Of course, every bodhisattva still has a lot of old bad seeds.
And every Bodhisattva,
even who has seen emptiness directly or
had this bodhisattva experience,
bodhichitta experience directly,
they still have a lot of bad seeds in their mind.
They still make mistakes.
They have not eliminated the the mental afflictions.
They are not arhats yet.
They still have a lot of problems. Okay?
But,
they can clean their mind out relatively faster than,
than other people, okay?
Number seven:
CI BSAM PA 'GRUB PA,
Any goal, spiritual goal, you set your mind to you can achieve it.
I would like to
learn, master Sanskrit, so I could help more people or something like that or,
you know.
I don't know, i'd like to be able to tell the future
and then I could help people more. So whatever you
dream of,
you're able to achieve it.
Number eight;
GNOD PA DANG BAR CHAD KYIS MI TSUGS PA,
You don't get extraordinary
obstacles. Okay. They, they avoid you.
We'll talk, by the way, each one of these has a long explanation
which is coming. I'm just giving you the ten quickly.
SA LAM THAMS CAD MYUR DU RDZOGS PA
You can move up through the
bodhisattva levels,
you can
get through the five paths
very, very quickly and reach the end. Number 10:
'GRO BA'I BDE SKYID MA LUS PA 'BYUNG BA'I ZHING SAR 'GYUR BA'O,,
You become a farmer's field in which
all of the wishes of every living being can grow and be
eaten yummy, yummily?  Later. Something like that.
Alright.
So we're going to talk about the first one, we still have some time.
We're going to talk about this first, we're going to talk about the first of the ten cool things
that happens to you
if you can get to this core experience.
) DANG PO NI,
And,
and I'd like to, I like to think,
okay, so,
when I was a kid
my parents got divorced
and my mother had no skills and no money,
and she went to school.
At that time the only job a woman could get was a secretary or a school teacher.
And she went to school and became a school teacher. And she had four
boys,
no money and
you know, our, our life was, it wasn't like we were hungry
regularly. Once in a while, we were hungry but,
but we had to be careful with money. And
I remember one day she said "Okay boys, we're going to have a family meeting"
And we all got there and she said,
"Look
we don't have so much money
so we're going to make this democratic.
We either have money to go see movies once in a while
or I have money to put you in the tennis club.
You can learn to play tennis in the tennis club."
Then we said, "Mom, we'll let you know."
And all four brothers we went to another room and we we were talking it over.
You know, like," Do you want, let's go see movies. Yeah, I mean who wants to play tennis?"
and they're like, "Yeah, let's vote for the movies." And then
my older brother said, "No, no, mom's trying to trick you"
And we said, "Well, what do you mean?" "Oh, she wants you to vote for the movies because it's cheaper
and the tennis club is more expensive. And we said, "But we don't want to learn tennis."
He says, "You, you deuce, deuce means dumb guy. You deuce. The tennis club has a swimming pool,
you can go swimming anytime you want.
She didn't tell you that because it's more expensive. Vote for the, vote for the tennis club
and then we get to go to the swimming pool anytime we want." We all voted for the tennis club.
And then my mom decided we had to learn tennis
to swim in the pool. So we learned tennis. She thought,
if, I think if yoga had existed it would have been yoga.
But she said, "Oh, this is something that will keep you fit for the rest of your life."
it doesn't, it's not like football you do football until you're 20 years old and
then you hurt your knees and you stop.
Or soccer, but tennis you can play. She played tennis until a few weeks before she died.
So she said, "This is good. This is going to be good for your whole life." So we learned.
But in my youth, tennis was considered very wimpy and only,
only like weird kids, weird skinny kids, don't show this one yet.
That's the punchline. Only weird kids...
You have to show the last one.
This, this little kid
little boys with buck teeth, you know, they,
this looks like Seiji when he's a kid actually.
Only weird kids who want to play tennis.
Why are we talking about that?
Later when I got to high school they had a tennis team
and,
and if you made it on the team, there were only five guys allowed on the team, six.
Only six guys allowed on the team.
And if you made it on the team
you got a special jacket and if you had this special jacket,
it was very easy to get a girlfriend. So we all wanted this special jacket. Letter,
letter jacket.
We all wanted one, so I'm like, "Yeah, I know tennis I can, I can get on the team.
So I was trying really hard to get on the team. This little guy with the tennis racket is me.
uh
"I want to get on the team mom."
Okay, here we go
DANG PO NI, DE LA THEG CHEN GYI GRAL DU CHUD MI CHUD KYANG,
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS 'DI RGYUD LA SKYES MA SKYES KYIS BYED PA YIN,
The question of whether you get on the team called bodhisattvas depends on whether you have this experience or not.
Got it? So if you want to get on the tennis team, meaning if you want to be on the bodhisattva team,
you have to have this experience. That's the first benefit
of having this experience with all living beings. If you have it
you're in this special club, you get the special bodhisattva jacket, all the bodhisattva girls fall in love with you.
Or the boys.
Uh, okay.
It's a long stretch but just put up with it.
RJE BLA MAS KYANG,
CHOS THEG CHEN YIN PAS MI CHOG GI, GANG ZAG THEG CHEN PAR TSUD PA ZHIG DGOS,
even Tsongkapa said,
"I don't care if the book you're reading is a bodhisattva book or not. Seiji is supposed to translate the Bodhisattva's Way of Life."
Tsongkapa was like, "I don't care,
I want to know if you'll join the club or not?"
THEG CHEN PAR TSUD means
are you one of those select vip
people
who has joined the bodhisattva club, who has had that experience?
That's the only thing I want to know. I don't care what book you're reading. I don't care
what books you're studying? I don't care if you're translating
my other books. I want to know have you had that experience or not?"
THEG CHEN PAR BYED PA YANG
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS NYID LA RAG LAS PAS
And whether you've joined that club only depends on whether you've had that experience.
SEMS DE GO BA TZAM LAS MED NA THEG CHEN PA YANG DE DANG 'DRA LA,
And if your
experience of that experience is just Geshe Michael
telling you about that experience,
then you are also that kind of bodhisattva.
We just talk about you like bodhisattva, but you're not.
You're not on the bodhisattva traxcct.
You just can repeat what someone said about it. Okay.
All right, DE DANG 'DRA LA, ZHES SOGS GSUNGS PA BZHIN,
Je Tsongkapa said that.
BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS 'DI RGYUD LA MED NA
So suppose you don't have this experience?
and RGYUD RGYAL, RGYUD RGYAL  means a king of all tantras.
MTHAR THUG, the ultimate king of all tantras.
DPAL GSANG BA 'DUS PA, Guhyasamaja,
which was one of one of Tsongkapa's favorite tantras.
His real favorite was Vajra Yogini, but that's secret.
'DUS PA LTA BU'I BSKYED RDZOGS NYAMS SU BLANGS KYANG.
You can practice
the two stages of tantra from the highest tantric book there is
But, KYANG,
'TSANG RGYU, TSANG RGYA RGYU LTA ZHOG
That's not going to make you a Buddha.
,THEG CHEN TSOGS LAM TZAM DU'ANG ZHUGS MI THUB,
That tantra won't even enable you to enter the first of the five paths on the bodhisattva track.
So forget the tantras, try to have this experience.
Do what you can to have this experience. How to have it:
study,
the two methods we have exchanging self and others, exchanging and equalizing.
Equalizing and exchanging yourself and others,
and then the seven, step method
taught by Lord Atisha. We're gonna study it.
All right
DE PHAR ZHOG ,THEG PA CHEN PO'I CHOS SU'ANG MI 'GRO LA,
If you're studying, if you're studying mahayana
and you haven't had this experience
then I would question whether you are studying. mahayana.That's kind of heavy.
SEMS 'DI YOD NA
But,
if you have had this experience,
MA nI TSAR GCIG BTON PA'ANG THEG CHEN GYI CHOS
and all you know how to do is OM MANI PEDME HUNG, OM MANI PEDME HUNG,
one time around on your rosary, that becomes the study of the mahayana teachings.
THEG CHEN SU 'GRO YANG
'TSANG RGYA BA'I RGYUR 'GRO STE,
And that one time of reciting that mantra on your rosary
will be enough to get you enlightened.
Okay, last
thing,
to show you is this picture.
And, you ready?
I found it today
You know me and Veronica found it but, uh,
anyway, uh, I did make the team.
And it was cool. That guy in the middle with the hair.
uh
is
so...
So it is possible to make this team
And whether or not you make this team, it just depends on learning those methods.
Equalizing and exchanging yourself and others and then just keep trying, just keep doing it
sincerely,
and you will have that experience. Then there's,
and then your life
has been valuable. Then you've had a good life if you just have that experience you have a good life.
Okay
See you then in episode 12.
You